Register of the Denison Kitchel Papers, 1947-1980
Hoover Institution Archives
Denison Kitchel Papers,
1947-1980
81127
Kitchel, Denison
5 manuscript boxes (2.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, and clippings, relating to American politics, and especially to the 1964 presidential campaign of Barry Goldwater.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Presidents--United States--Election--1964.; United States--Politics and government.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Conservatism.
Scope and Content
Denison Kitchel was born on March 1, 1908 in Bronxville, New York. After completing his B.A. at Yale University, he entered Harvard Law School from which he received his LL.B. in 1933. Upon finishing his studies, he moved to Arizona where he was admitted to the bar in 1934. His initial position was with Ellinwood and Ross; in 1946, along with two other lawyers, he founded the firm of Evans, Kitchel and Jenckes in Phoenix. In 1970 he retired from practice.
Denison Kitchel was active in Republican politics in Arizona from about 1950 on. His primary association was with Barry Goldwater - as friend, advisor, and general manager of Senator Goldwater's campaign for the presidency in 1964. The Barry Goldwater file, spanning the years from 1947 to 1980, is the largest file in the correspondence series and, perhaps, the richest and most reward- ing relevant to political events. The researcher should be aware that other important Goldwater material, including correspondece, is located in all of the other series excepting Miscellaneous. Other noteworthy correspondents in the correspondence series include William J. Baroody, president of the American Enterprise Institute; Paul Fannin, senator from and governor of Arizona; author and political observer Raymond Moley; Supreme Court Justice William H. Rehnquist; Arizona Congressmen John J. Rhodes and Sam Steiger; and Arizona Governor Jack Williams.
The Goldwater Presidential Campaign series is small and limited, both in scope and in content. Much of the material in it is commonplace, particluarly the general correspondence section and the voluminous congratulatory correspondence received by Kitchel. Those letters from the correspondence subseries of the Goldwater Presidential Campaign series which were deemed more substantial and interesting were placed in the general Correspondence series discussed in the preceeding paragraph. Of greatest note in the Goldwater Presidential series would be the "Draft Goldwater Endeavor" file, material of which spans the years 1962 - 1963. This file offers a short but interesting account of the genesis of the Goldwater presidential camapign.
The Office File contains material relevant to a few different legal issues in which Mr. Kitchel was, to a greater or lesser extent, involved. Informative in their own right, the various files within the Office File series also yield information on Mr. Kitchel's legal opinions and thinking.
Approximately the same size as the last two series is the Speeches and Writings series. The various items are listed either by subject or by title. The most detailed, and perhaps most interesting, entry is that of "Explaining Things to Ike." The article specifically concerns a meeting between Goldwater and Eisenhower at which Senator Goldwater's statement "extremism in defense of liberty is no vice," is explained to the former President. The files for that particular article contain drafts, revisions and correspondence relating to the genesis of Senator Goldwater's phrase.
There is also a very small Miscellany File.
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1947-1980 (Boxes 1-3)
  Correspodence of Denison Kitchel, including carbons and xeroxes of outgoing letters, arranged alphabetically by correspondent and thereunder chronologically.
- GOLDWATER PRESIDENTIAL CAMPAIGN, 1964, 1962-1965 (Boxes 3-4)
  Correspondence, memoranda, notes, newspaper and magazine articles relating to Barry Goldwater's campaign for the presidency in 1964. Material is arranged alphabetically by subject and thereunder chronologically.
- OFFICE FILE, 1963-1975 (Boxes 4-5)
  Correspondence, articles, memoranda, decisions and opinion papers relating to various legal matters. Arranged alphabetically by subject or title and thereunder chronologically.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1956-1976 (Box 5)
  Drafts and final versions of articles and speeches written by Denison Kitchel. Included in this file is correspondence relevant to the writing of some of the pieces. Arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
- MISCELLANY, ca. 1962-1966 (Box 5)
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1947-1980
  - General. (Box 1)
    - Undated, 1950-1965.
    - 1966-1970.
    - 1971-1980.
  - Allen, Richard V. 1969.
  - American Association of Presidents of Indepen- dent Colleges and Universities. 1973.
  - American Institute for Political Communication. 1967.
  - Angle, Jerry L. 1968.
  - Arizona Republic (formerly Phoenix Republic and Gazette). 1956-1975.
  - Astley, Joan (Mrs. Philip). 1965-1969.
  - Ayau, Manuel F. 1970-1978.
  - Baroody, William J. 1965-1974.
  - Beebe, Lucius. 1965.
  - Bisbee Council on the Arts and Humanities. 1972.
  - Blackburn, Richard A. 1973-1976.
  - Bliss, Ray. 1965-1968.
  - Bobbs-Merrill Co. 1968.
  - Bridget, Lou (Mrs. Bernard A.). 1978-1979.
  - Brock, Horace. 1979.
  - Brown, Howard K. 1968.
  - Brown, Thatcher M. 1970.
  - Buckley, William F. 1973-1979.
  - Burch, Dean. 1965-1971.
  - Bush, George. 1976-1980.
  - Campbell, Rita Ricardo. 1969.
  - Campbell, W. Glenn. 1965-1969.
  - Capen, Richard G., Jr. 1969.
  - Chamber of Commerce of the United States. 1965.
  - Charles, Scott. 1979.
  - Claremont Men's College. 1967.
  - Coconino County Women's Republican Club. 1967.
  - Conlan, John B. 1973.
  - Copley, James. 1971.
  - Cordiner, Ralph J. 1965.
  - Crawford, Ronald. 1971-1975.
  - Curtis, John A. 1971-1972.
  - Davenport, John. 1978-1979.
  - Davis, Loyal. 1980.
  - Day, Henry L. 1964.
  - Dodge, Polly (Mrs. Cleveland E.). 1968.
  - Doolittle, J. H. 1965.
  - Douglas, James. 1965.
  - Douglas, Lew W. 1954-1969.
  - Dougles, P. L. 1963.
  - Dozer, Donald M. 1973.
  - Drum, James Hunter. 1978-1979. (Box 2)
  - Dunn, Rogers C. 1965.
  - Eaker, Ira C. 1951.
  - Evans, William A. 1967.
  - Fannin, Paul. 1960-1976.
  - Fenzi, Warren E. 1968.
  - Ferguson, Robert M. and Frannie. 1970-1975.
  - Feulner, Edward J. 1978-1979.
  - Ford, Gerald R. 1965-1973.
  - Friedman, Milton. 1966-1976.
  - Gardiner, H. E. 1969.
  - Glick, Edward M. 1966.
  - Godduhn, Arnold E. 1975.
  - Goldwater, Barry.
    - Undated, 1947-1963.
    - 1964-1970.
    - 1971-1972.
    - 1973-1980.
  - Grady, Jack. 1956.
  - Grange, Robert W. 1975-1978.
  - Greenway, John S. 1967.
  - Gregory, Charles O. 1950-1951.
  - Grenier, John E. 1965.
  - Griffin, James S. 1969.
  - Hall, A. C. 1965.
  - Harlan, John M. 1962-1967.
  - Hawkins, Jean (Mrs. Paul M.). Undated, 1965-1980.
  - Hayden, Carl. 1968.
  - Haynsworth, Clement F. 1977-1978.
  - Herberger, G. Robert. 1968.
  - Howell, John. 1980.
  - Humphrey, George M. 1964.
  - Jenckes, Joseph S., Jr. 1967-1973.
  - Johnson, Lyndon B. 1967.
  - Kelland, James P. 1967.
  - Kellar, Kenneth C. 1962-1979.
  - Kemp, Arthur. 1976.
  - Kitchel, James. 1967.
  - Kitchel, William L., II. 1965.
  - Klein, Herbert G. 1968.
  - Kleindienst, Richard G. 1969.
  - Kieran, John. 1965.
  - Knorpp, Walter W. 1968.
  - Laird, Melvin R. 1969-1973.
  - Lamb, Karl. 1965.
  - Lawrence, John T. 1965.
  - Laxalt, Paul. 1978.
  - Lay, Beirne, Jr. 1974-1980.
  - Luce, Clare Booth. 1964-1974.
  - McCabe, Edward A. 1968-1974. (Box 3)
  - McCarty, John T. 1971-1972.
  - Moley, Frances (Mrs. Raymond). 1975-1978.
  - Moley, Raymond. 1964-1974.
  - Moley, Raymond, Jr. 1971.
  - Mont Pelerin Society. 1966-1971.
  - Munroe, George. 1966-1980.
  - Nixon, Richard M. 1960-1968.
  - Nutter, Warren G. 1969.
  - O'Boyle, John W. 1951.
  - Orme, Charles H., Jr. 1966-1980.
  - Park, Edgar C. 1976.
  - Parkinson, Gaylord B. 1967.
  - Pearce, Charles A. 1968.
  - Phelps Dodge Corporation. 1956-1980.
  - Prescott College. 1966-1968.
  - Pritzlaff, John C., Jr. 1970-1974.
  - Proctor, Thomas E. 1967.
  - Randolph, Jo (Mrs. Howell S.). 1979.
  - Read, Leonard E. 1969-1976.
  - Reagan, Ronald. 1966-1980.
  - Rehnquist, William H. Undated, 1962-1980.
  - Republican National Committee. 1959-1972.
  - Republican State Committee (Arizona). 1963.
  - Rhodes, John J. 1953-1980.
  - Robb, Roger. 1968.
  - Roche, George. 1972-1978.
  - Rosenblatt, Paul. 1974.
  - Rowe, David N. 1980.
  - Royal, Robert. 1965.
  - Ruskin, Lewis J. 1965.
  - Schell, Orville H. 1979-1980.
  - Simpson, Milward L. 1966.
  - Smith, Tony. 1965.
  - Southern Arizona Bank and Trust Co. 1967-1970.
  - Steiger, Sam. 1968-1976.
  - Streit, Clarence K. 1965.
  - Sunderland, Thomas E. 1975.
  - Taft, Robert, Jr. 1965-1966.
  - Turner, William C. 1980.
  - Udall, Morris K. 1968.
  - Uren, William J. 1955-1979.
  - Vance, Henry T. 1965.
  - Van Dusen, Francis L. 1969.
  - Walker, Robert C. 1967.
  - Ware, Richard A. 1969.
  - Welch, Robert, Jr. 1960.
  - White, Theodor H. 1965.
  - Wickersham, Cornelius. 1964-1965.
  - Williams, Jack. 1966-1974.
  - Wilson, Robert F. 1967-1969.
  - Wormser, Felix Edgar. 1972.
  - Yale University. 1961-1980.
- GOLDWATER PRESIDENTIAL CAMPAIGN, 1964, 1962-1965
  - Articles, post-election. 1964. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, general. (Box 4)
    - 1963.
    - January 1 - November 1, 1964.
    - November 21 - December 28, 1964.
    - January 6 - April 30, 1965.
  - Draft Goldwater Endeavor. Notes, memoranda and correspondence. 1962-1963.
  - Meet The Press - Congratulatory letters to Denison Kitchel. June 1964.
  - Newspaper articles. 1963.
  - Republican National Committee - Post-election statements. January 12, 1965.
  - Republican National Convention - Congratulatory letters to Denison Kitchel. July - August 1964.
  - Task Forces - Correspondence and memoranda. 1964.
- OFFICE FILE, 1963-1975
  - Copper Tariff Board - Correspondence and memoranda relating to Denison Kitchel's appointment to the Arizona Copper Tariff Board. 1967-1975. (Box 4)
  - Legal Services Corporation - Correspondence and articles relating to the consideration of Denison Kitchel as chariman of the Legal Services Corporation. 1974-1975. (Box 5)
  - Canadian Arctic Waters - Correpsondence and documents relating to proposed legislation in Canadian parliament. April - August 1970.
  - Nuclear Test Ban Treaty - Correspondence and notes relating to consideration of treaty by U.S. Senate. 1963.
  - "Whitewater Draw" - Court case and opinions. April 1975.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1956-1976
  - Eulogy for Raymond Moley, February 22, 1975. Xerox, 2 copies. (Box 5)
  - "Explaining Things to Ike."
    - Draft, "Extremism in Defense of Liberty." Xerox copies.
    - Draft, "Extremism in Defense of Liberty," annotated by Denison Kitchel.
    - Draft, "Extremism in Defense of Liberty," annotated by Barry Goldwater.
    - Final version, "Explaining Things to Ike." National Review, April 30, 1976.
    - Correspondence.
      - General. 1969-1976.
      - Baroody, William J. 1969-1974.
      - Campbell, W. Glenn. 1969.
      - Goldwater, Barry. 1969-1976.
      - Jaffa, Prof. Harry. 1969-1976.
      - Latimer, Prof. John F. 1969.
      - Moley, Raymond, 1969-1974.
      - National Review. 1975-1976.
  - Goldwater speech given to Iternational Railway Brotherhood of Engineers. Phoenix, October 14, 1968. Xerox.
  - "A Plea for Political Integrity." Speech given at Morenci, Arizona, January 27, 1960. Typescript, carbon.
  - Senate Select Committee of Intelligece, 1975.
    - Correspondence, general. 1975.
    - "Memorandum on the Constitutional Aspects of Covert Action Operations in the Field of Foreign Relations." September 5, 1975. Xerox.
  - "Sound-Off Section." July 4, 1973. Xerox.
  - "The United States at EXPO 67." 1967. Type- script.
  - Voice of Free Enterprise (newspaper column).
    - Blueprint for column.
    - Newspaper clippings and xeroxes of columns, February 5 - November 18, 1956.
    - Typescripts, October 21, November 4, and November 11, 1956.
  - Watergate speech by Barry Goldwater, co-authored by Raymond Moley. 1974. Xerox.
- MISCELLANEOUS, ca. 1962-1966
  - General (Box 5)